<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Apache Torque</title>
    <author email="jvanzyl@apache.com">Jason van Zyl</author>
    <author email="mpoeschl@marmot.at">Martin Poeschl</author>
    <author email="seade@backstagetech.com.au">Scott Eade</author>
    <author email="hps@intermeta.de">Henning P. Schmiedehausen</author>
    <author email="fischer@seitenbau.de">Thomas Fischer</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
   <section name="What is Torque?">
     <p>
       Apache Torque is an object-relational mapper for java. 
       In other words, Torque lets you access and manipulate data
       in a relational database using java objects.
       Unlike most other object-relational mappers, Torque does not use
       reflection to access user-provided classes, but it generates the
       necessary classes (including the Data Objects) from an XML schema
       describing the database layout. The XML file can either be written
       by hand or a starting point can be generated from an existing database.
       The XML schema can also be used to generate and execute a SQL script
       which creates all the tables in the database.
     </p>
     
     <p>
       As Torque hides database-specific implementation details, 
       Torque makes an application independent of a specific database
       if no exotic features of the database are used.
     </p>
     
     <p>
       Usage of code generation eases the customization of the database layer, 
       as you can override the generated methods and thus easily change
       their behavior. A modularized template structure allows inclusion
       of your own code generation templates during the code generation process.
     </p>
     
     <p>
       Torque 5.0 and 5.1 requires JDK 1.8 or higher. Torque 4.0 requires JDK 1.6 or higher.
         Also labelled version 5.0 it is still considered highly compatible with version 4.
       Current development version is 5.2-SNAPSHOT.
     </p>
   </section>

   <section name="Releases">
    <p>
     <ul>
      <li>
        The most recent <i>production</i> release of Torque is 
        <a href="http://db.apache.org/torque">Torque 5.1</a>.
      </li>
       <li>
        The previous stable <i>production</i> release is 
        <a href="http://db.apache.org/torque/torque-4.0">Torque 4.0</a>.
      </li>
     </ul>
    </p>
   </section>

   <section name="Elements of Torque 4 and 5">
    <p>
     Torque consists of multiple parts:
     <dl>
       <dt>torque-runtime</dt>
       <dd>
        The Torque Runtime contains everything to allow an
        application to access the database.  It is the only component of Torque
        needed in your application and can be used standalone.
       </dd>
       <dt>torque-generator</dt>
       <dd>
         The Torque Generator is a general-purpose code generator
         which can be used to generate the O/R classes, SQL scripts
         etc for OR Mapping, but can also be used for other code generation
         purposes.
         If you use the Torque Maven Plugin or Torque Ant Tasks,
         you do not need to use the generator directly.
       </dd>
       <dt>maven-torque-plugin</dt>
       <dd>
        The Torque Maven Plugin makes the Torque generator accessible
        in a Maven 2/3 build.
       </dd>
       <dt>torque-ant-tasks</dt>
       <dd>
        The Torque Ant tasks integrate the Torque generator in an Ant build.
       </dd>
       <dt>torque-templates</dt>
       <dd>
         The Torque Templates contain the building blocks used by the generator 
         to create the O/R classes, SQL scripts and the like.
         You can extend or change the templates if you want to customize
         the output of the generator, or even write templates of your own.
       </dd>
     </dl>
    </p>
   </section>
   <section name="The Apache Software Foundation">
     <p>
      Torque is an <a href="www.apache.org">Apache</a> project,
      and is part of a larger community of developers and users.
     </p>
     <p>
      Apache Torque, Torque, Apache, the Apache feather logo,
      and the Apache Torque project logo are trademarks of 
      <a href="www.apache.org">The Apache Software Foundation</a>.
     </p>
   </section>
  </body>
</document>
