<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Editing and Deploying the Torque site</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
   <section name="Introduction">
     <p>
       This document is addressed to Torque committers who wish to edit and
       deploy the Torque site.  If you find anything missing or wrong,
       please edit this document.  If you find any procedure unsatisfactory,
       change it and document it here :-).
     </p>
   </section>
   
   <section name="Site source code and build process">
     <p>
       The complete Torque site resides in the module torque-site.
       Only the reports from the subprojects are pulled into the main
       site via a process documented below.
       The subprojects do not have an own xdoc subdirectory.
     </p>
     <p>
       For a local build of the site, cd into the torque parent dir and run
       <code>mvn post-site</code> (if you just run <code>mvn site</code>,
       the reports from the other modules will not be pulled in).
       When finished, the site can be found in 
       torque-site/target/site.
     </p>
     <subsection name="Transferring the module reports to the main site">
       <p>
         The project reports of the subprojects are pulled into the
         main site during the site lifecycle of the main site. 
         This happens in the following automated steps, which are defined
         in the pom.xml of the torque-site module:
       </p>
       <ul>
         <li>
           In the pre-site phase, the reports are copied from the
           site directories of the respective modules to the target directory
           of the site module 
           (directories generator-site, runtime-site, ...).
           They are renamed to xml, the doctype header
           is removed, and in some cases xhtml errors are fixed.
         </li>  
         <li>
           In the site phase, the copied reports are transformed by the xslt
           stylesheet torque-site/src/site/xslt/body-content.xsl
           such that only the body part remains and the "page frame"
           is omitted. The result is written to the directories
           generator-site-content, runtime-site-content...
         </li>
         <li>
           In the post-site phase, the body parts of the report are
           inserted into the placeholder pages which sources can be found in
           torque-site/src/site/xdoc/documentation/modules/generator/reports,
           torque-site/src/site/xdoc/documentation/modules/runtime/reports...
           Some reports do not need to be transformed, e.g. the
           cobertura report, the javadocs and the sources xref, they are copied
           unchanged.
         </li>
      </ul>
     </subsection>
   </section>
   
   <section name="Deploying the site">
     <p>
       This is a step-by-step guide to deploy the whole site. 
       
       Follow the recommendations in <a href="https://infra.apache.org/publishing-maven-artifacts.html">Apache Infrastructure Information concerning Publishing Maven artifacts</a>. 
      Recent releases do not use ssh deployment anymore, but instead the <a href="https://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-scm-publish-plugin/">scm-publishing</a> mechanism. 
      </p> 
   <subsection name="Step by step">
     <p>
       Now you can begin to build and deploy the site:
     </p>
     <ul>
       <li>
         run <i>mvn clean post-site</i> in the torque parent (root) module.
         <source><![CDATA[
        mvn clean post-site  ]]>
         </source>
       </li>
       <li>
         check the site in <strong>torque-site/target/site</strong>
       </li>
       <li>
         It might be a good idea to create a tar.gz or zip backup of the current
         state of the site in your apache home directory, in case anything goes
         wrong.
         Find the current site in pom.xml: project->distributionManagement->site->url.
       </li>
       <li>
         run <i>mvn site:deploy</i> in the torque-site module. This should trigger <i>mvn scm-publish:publish-scm</i>.
          <source><![CDATA[
        mvn site:deploy  ]]>
         </source>
         
       </li>
       <li>
         Wait till the site is rsynced to the apache web servers
         (might take some hours). Alternatively, check 
         <a href="http://www.apache.org/dev/project-site.html">http://www.apache.org/dev/project-site.html</a>
         for a proxy setting which allows to look at the newly deployed site
         before the rsync happens,
         but this might not work under all circumstances.
       </li>
       <li>
         Empty the cache of your browser and check everything is ok on
         <a href="http://db.apache.org/torque/torque-5.0/index.html">http://db.apache.org/torque/torque-5.0/index.html</a>
       </li>
       <li>
         If you are satisfied with the new site and no-one complains during
         the next few days, delete the backup tar.gz or zip.
       </li>
     </ul>
    </subsection>
   </section>
   
   <section name="Updating the site for a new release">
     <ul>
       <li>
         Check that all version numbers are up to date, especially in the
         tutorial, usage pages and on the download page.
       </li>
       <li>
         Check that the correct internal version id is in the configuration
         <i>fixVersionIds</i> of the maven-changes-plugin in the pom of the
         torque-site project. The correct number can be determined by opening
         the torque project in jira, clicking on "versions" in the left menu,
         click on the appropriate version and then on "release notes" on top
         of the site. The version number is the number appearing last in the
         URL of the page. 
       </li>
     </ul>
   </section>

  </body>
</document>
